Mss.Rec.242 Mss.Rec.242
American Philosophical Society
Ghost Dance-era Songs of the Arapaho Crow Dance
1995
Mss.Rec.242
American Philosophical Society
5.0 Tape(s)
Linguistic and cultural fieldwork about songs associated with the Crow Dance of the Northern Arapaho and its relation to the Ghost Dance and other tribes' dances. Consists of linguistic and cultural analysis and transcription of 16 pre-recorded songs sung by Fred Gone, Sr. an with Arapaho consultant, William C'Hair. Also includes extensive discussion of Arapaho customs and ceremonies. Recorded in Arapahoe, Wyoming on 18 July 1995.
5 sound tape reels (4 hr., 44 min.): analog, 3 3/4 ips, half track, mono; 7 in.
C'Hair, Wayne
C'Hair, William
Gone, Fred, Sr.
Hatton, Orin T.
Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Presented by Orrin Hatton. This material was recorded with the assistance of a Phillips Fund grant.
Related Archival Materials
Project report, correspondence among researchers and consultant, song texts with notes, song transcriptions, subject index and finding aid to interview tapes, transcript of tape 1, and various linguistic and melodic analyses can be found in the Phillips Fund Collection (Mss.497.3.Am4).
Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Arapaho Indians--Social life and customs; Arapaho language; Ghost dance; Sound recordings
- Audio recordings
  - Introductory remarks and discussion of songs, 1995-07-18; 01-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:29:37; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    Scope and Contents note
    "Opening discussion about translation of 'my children' and use in song, singular or plural. Introductions. Discussion of the order of song performance (tape collection has a random order). Description of the Gone songs and their use (not ceremonial songs). Discussion about notation of Arapaho language in IPA. C'Hair is conversant in linguistic notation, accustomed to writing his language and working as a linguistic and cultural consultant. Discussion of songtexts; compression of words in songs."
    Existence and Location of Originals note
    This file is a compressed, digitized version of the original. The APS Library maintains the original format (Sound tape reel) as well as an uncompressed digitized version of this recording.
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho language; Arapahoe (Wyo.)
  - Song #1, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 01-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:28:07; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #1. [3:05 - 6:50] Discussion follows: Arapaho text, notation, and English translation; 'day of wind'. Irrelevant discussion of Indian word for St. Louis and reference to Mexicans or Spaniards as 'bread people.' Discussion of misappropriation of term 'Crow Dance' for the 'Dance of God'; language used in prayers; Jack Wilson (Wovoka) and Ghost Dance; origins of 'Dance of God' from the Sioux people; Omaha dance from the Omaha people (wolf people), 'Wolf Dance'; Rabbit Dance and Owl Dance."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho language; Arapahoe (Wyo.); Omaha dance; Sioux dance
  - Discussion of the transcripton of Song #1, 1995-07-18; 02-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:56; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Discussion of song text transcription; clarification of nature of songs in Gone/Taylor collection (significance to Arapaho people)."
  - Song #2, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 02-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:56; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #2. Further discussion of use of singular and plural; song compression issue; text: 'where the water runs out' or 'real wooden dishes'?"
  - Song #3, The Bow Song, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 02-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:26; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #3. Pronunciation of words to facilitate pitch notation. The Bow Song; the singer is emulating thunder, drumming upon the earth; discussion of wearing bow and plume."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Clothing & dress; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho language; Arapahoe (Wyo.); dress
  - Song #4, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 02-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:40; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #4. Discussion of verb meaning to roar like thunder."
  - Continuing discussion of Song #4, 1995-07-18; 02-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:19; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Discussion of fitting words to melody; origin of term 'push up' for introductory phrases in powwow songs; singing instructions; attempts to elicit song terminology; singers are 'eagles' or keepers of songs."
  - Song #5, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 02-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:51; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #5. Comparison of Gros Ventre and Arapaho pronunciation; discussion of words excluding speaker and person to."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho language; Arapahoe (Wyo.); Atsina language
  - Song #6, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 02-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:05:50; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #6. Discussion of additions and compression of text to fit melody of song; mention of old tape of Gros Ventre speaking by Robert Mount."
  - Continued discussion of Song #6, 1995-07-18; 03-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:15; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Further discussion of song #6; significance of context to facilitate understanding of text."
  - Song #7, The Spoon Song, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 03-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:46; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #7. The Spoon Song. Replacement of initial glottal stop with an /h/ and subsequent change in meaning; description of spoon made of buffalo horn with quillwork decorations (this is paraphrenalia from 'dance of god'; discussion of other ritual paraphrenalia--whistle, bowl, quirt, spear, fork stick, spoon, kingfisher."
  - Song #8, Song for the Keeper of the Bow, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 03-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:44; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #8. Song for the Keeper of the Bow. Discussion of song text and transcription; launching vowel."
  - Song #9, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 03-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:10:44; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #9. Gros Ventre text; song goes with the paint ceremony; discussion of singular and plural usage; red paint; mourning customs."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Arapaho language; Arapahoe (Wyo.); Atsina language
  - Song #10, Buffalo Chaser Song, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 03-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:26:26; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Discussion of getting together for follow up. Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #10. Buffalo Chaser Song. Extensive discussion of song text, apparent meaning; discussion of transcription(s); speculation on meaning of songtext."
  - Song #11, Song for the Whistle Carrier, 1995-07-18; 03-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:28; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #11. Song for the Whistle Carrier."
  - Discussion of Song #11, Song for the Whistle Carrier, 1995-07-18; 04-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:34; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Discussion of song #11; discussion of text and transcription."
  - Song #12, Second song for the Whistle Carrier, 'I am also a magpie,' with discussion, 1995-07-18; 04-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:19:06; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #12. Second song for the Whistle Carrier; Carrier dances to this song. 'I am also a magpie'; discussion of pronunciation; discussion of magpie's special attributes; discussion of cardinal versus red-tailed hawk; discussion of circumstances that might precipitate a vow leading to sponsorship of ceremony."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Arapaho language; Arapahoe (Wyo.); Black-billed magpie
  - Discussion of sacrifice of pup and Crow Dance, 1995-07-18; 04-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:04:45; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "[D]iscussion of preparations for cooking a pup in ceremony; participation of Eagle Society in ceremony; whip man and Black Bird Dance."
    Animal sacrifice; Arapaho Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Arapahoe (Wyo.)
  - Discussion of whip dance, sacrifice of pup, and Eagle Society, 1995-07-18; 04-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:17:31; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Further discussion of whip dance, bustle dance and sacrifice of pup; discussion of human sacrifice and cannibalism; more on eating pup. Questions for consultant attempting to clarify points relative to sacrifice of pup; no real parallels with Assiniboine Kettle Drum ritual; pup is sacred food, but not the same significane up north; discussion of songs and Fred Gone. Discussion of Ronald Lah's work with Arapaho music; further comparison with Assiniboine Kettle Dance; participation of Eagle Society; whip man's responsibilities in old days and today."
    Animal sacrifice; Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapaho Indians--Social life and customs; Arapahoe (Wyo.)
  - Song #13, "Whirlwind song--'that is my flag,'" with discussion, 1995-07-18; 04-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:30; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #13. 'Whirlwind song--'that is my flag'. Probably not a song to dance to; discussion of text and pronunciation."
  - Song #14, "I fly around the sky," with discussion, 1995-07-18; 04-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:03:14; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #14. Song--'I fly around the sky'; a good traditional dance song; you are the eagle, the spirit of the eagle."
  - Song #15, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 05-01; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:17; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #15. Discussion of song text and pronunciation, transcription; preparation of paint; discussion of colors and paints; other consultants for certain topics."
  - Song #16, with discussion, 1995-07-18; 05-02; 1.0 .mp3; 00:12:06; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Gone, Fred P.; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Play tape of [Fred] Gone singing song #16. Discussion of song text and pronunciation; pitches; switches for what Gone thought to be correct Arapaho; word boundaries; red clouds and 'where I fly'; discussion of terminology for various snow conditions."
  - Discussion of the origins of Ghost Dance and Crow Dance, 1995-07-18; 05-03; 1.0 .mp3; 00:09:19; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Discussion of origins of Ghost Dance, Crow Dance, and significance/role of Yellow Calf to these ceremonies. Discussion of families associated with paraphrenalia used in 'dance of god' ceremony."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Music; Arapahoe (Wyo.); Ghost dance
  - Discussion of reservation districts, ceremony staging and naming, and names for Pawnee and Omaha people, 1995-07-18; 05-04; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:29; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "Discussion of reservation districts; possibility of staging the ceremony this fall/winter; difficulty of changing the name of the ceremony at this late date; names for Pawnee and Omaha people."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Arapaho Indians--Social life and customs; Arapahoe (Wyo.); Omaha Indians; Pawnee Indians
  - Discussion of feather bustle construction, 1995-07-18; 05-05; 1.0 .mp3; 00:06:14; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Clothing & dress; Arapaho Indians--Rites and ceremonies; Arapahoe (Wyo.); dress
  - Discussion of significance of dance to Indian people, 1995-07-18; 05-06; 1.0 .mp3; 00:01:21; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "[N]o such thing as war dance."
    Arapaho dance; Arapahoe (Wyo.); Indians of North America--Dance
  - Discussion of the order and purpose of the songs, 1995-07-18; 05-07; 1.0 .mp3; 00:02:48; C'Hair, Wayne; C'Hair, William James; Hatton, Orin T., 1953-; Taylor, Allan R. (Allan Ross), 1931-
    "[William] C'Hair says these were fun sessions; songs cannot be put in order--not the ritual songs; these are honor songs for the keepers of the ritual paraphrenalia, and educational songs (i.e. the song they use when they honor the person that has the bow)."
    Arapaho dance; Arapaho Indians--Social life and customs; Arapahoe (Wyo.)